<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Amaryllis to Tityrus being the first heroick harangue of the excellent pen of Monsieur Scvdery, a witty and pleasant novel / Englished by a person of honour.</title>
            <author>Scudéry, Madeleine de, 1607-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58871</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10262</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11907118</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11907118</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50736</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58871)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50736)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 511:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Amaryllis to Tityrus being the first heroick harangue of the excellent pen of Monsieur Scvdery, a witty and pleasant novel / Englished by a person of honour.</title>
                  <author>Scudéry, Madeleine de, 1607-1701.</author>
                  <author>Person of honour.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 86, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will. Cademan ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Amaryllis to Tityrus is part of Les femmes illustres, variously attributed to Madeleine de Scudéry and to her brother Georges.  Cf. information in notes in Bib. nat. and NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2]-[8] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50736:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50736:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AMARYLLIS</hi> TO TITYRUS. Being, the Firſt HEROICK HARANGUE OF THE EXCELLENT PEN OF Monſieur <hi>SC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DERY.</hi> A Witty and Pleaſant NOVEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Engliſhed by a Perſon of Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Cademan,</hi> at the <hi>Pope's Head</hi> in the <hi>New Exchange.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:50736:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50736:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Amaryllis</hi> to <hi>Tityrus.</hi> THE FIRST HEROICK HARANGUE OF Monſieur <hi>de Scudery.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
               <p>The Great <hi>Virgil,</hi> introducing himſelf, in his <hi>Eclogues</hi> and his <hi>Bucolicks,</hi> under the Name of a Shepherd, called <hi>Tityrus,</hi> He regrets therein <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Court of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> (being far from it) be confeſſed himſelf to be very little ſatisfied with the Woods and Campaign: Which cauſed the Author to introduce him in this place, with his Miſtris <hi>Amarillis,</hi> who ſurprized him in this thought, and reproached him of the ſmall value he put on their Abode; repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to him its Beauties, and compares
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50736:3"/>'em to the defaults of that which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gretted; ſeeking to make him avow, That the Campaign Life is to be preferred to that of the City.</p>
            </argument>
            <head>AMARILLIS <hi>to</hi> TITYRUS.</head>
            <p>CEaſe, illuſtrious Shepherd, ceaſe to regret the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of <hi>Rome,</hi> and and trouble not the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of our Groves, by your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and inutile Plaints, and leave to perſwade us, That be it for the Agreement of Perſons, or Purity of Manners, or the Innocence of Pleaſures, or the Felicity of Life, or for veritable Vertues, our Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigns ought not to be preferred before the Pomp of the moſt cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Cities; and the ſimplicity of our Cabins, to the Abode of the moſt Superbe Palaces. I avow, that the deſcription which you have made of this Haughty Pride, which vaunts it ſelf of ſubjecting
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50736:3"/>all the Earth to it, is very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that which I have a deſign to ſhew you this day. In the one they ſee Crowns and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; in the other but Chaplets of Flowers and Sheep-hooks, In the firſt, they ſee but by the ſplendor of Gold, Pearls, and Diamonds; in that which I am about to ſhew, you ſhall ſee no other Gold than that of the Sun-beams; no other Pearls, than that of the Dew, ſpread over the Enamel of our Meads and Flowers; nor no other Diamonds, than the liquid Chryſtal of our Fountains: But, O <hi>Tityrus,</hi> how pure is this Gold, and what an agreeable Luſtre have theſe Pearls, and how delicious is this moving Chryſtal, to thoſe who leave not themſelves to be blinded with falſe Appearances; and He who knows to do as he ought, diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Beauties of Art from thoſe of Nature, and prefers, with Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a durable Felicity from that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50736:4"/>which paſſes away. You will ſay to me, perhaps, What do I mean to ſpeak ſo, it ſeemeth as if I had but little conſidered the Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent deſcription of the Portraiture that you have made me ſee of the Court of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> ſince I accord not with you, that you have cauſe to complain of being ſo far from it; 'tis true, I have remarked all the Lines out, and I avow, that at the firſt, the ſight of theſe great Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Marble, of Jaſper, and Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyry, have made me doubt, if I ought not to prefer 'em to our <hi>Grots;</hi> however, I have not been any long time in this Error, and though, without doubt, this Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture is not a little flattering, I have not left to know, that you are in the wrong, to ſpeak of <hi>Rome</hi> as of a place in which nothing is wanting to render an honeſt man happy; and of our Foreſts, as of an Abode where one can find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which can reaſonably ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50736:4"/>a Perſon of Spirit. Examine all theſe things in order, I conjure you, and forget not to hear me attentively, and to perſwade you more ſtrongly, I ſhall let you ſee that <hi>Rome</hi> is, in my imagination, ſuch as you have depainted it, to the end, that by the oppoſition of the Life of the Court, and that of the Countrey, I may make you ſee the Advantages and the Defaults of the one and the other, that I may lead you the more eaſily into my Senſe. You have ſaid to me (if I deceive not my ſelf) that the Beauty of the places where they inhabit, ſerve very much to render men happy; and that fine Objects elevate the Spirit; and, that this being ſo (as I avow it,) <hi>Rome</hi> is the moſt charming Abode in the World, ſince that it is there, where one may find the moſt ſplendid Objects: You have, I ſay, aſſured me, that all the Temples there are filled with the Works of all the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50736:5"/>greateſt Maſters of Antiquity; that all the Furniture is Superbe, and that all the publick Places are adorned either with Statues of Braſs, or with Triumphant Arches; and that, in fine, ſhe ſhuts up in her Walls all that which Art can produce of marvellous, and all that which is moſt rare in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. We ſhall ſee after this, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Shepherd, if I ſhall find in our Solitudes wherewith to make you forget ſuch fair Objects, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to make you confeſs, that a Campaign Life is preferrable to that of the City. I ſee well that you find my Deſign too hardy, and that you have pain to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend (you, I ſay, who have never loved the place where you were born, and who have forgotten it:) that out of <hi>Rome</hi> one can ſee any thing of marvellous, nevertheleſs, there is a notable difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Ornaments that embel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it, and thoſe of the place where
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50736:5"/>we inhabit; Art is that which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it Fair; on the contrary with us, we rejoyce of all the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Nature; in fine, ſhe's but the Work of men, and our Abode is the chief Work of the Gods. It is true, we have no Palaces, but if our Cabins are leſs Magnificent, they are by their lowneſs farther from Lightning, and Tempeſts. And then, to ſay the truth, whoever ſets himſelf to conſider the marvellous Structure of the frettiſed Canopy over our Heads, regretteth not the moſt Superbe Cielings at <hi>Rome.</hi> But, ſhall I tell you, that it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as though you ſtudied to tell me, that the Stars, and the Sun, each one in their courſes, enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en not the Capitol, and that <hi>Rome</hi> is but a place of obſcurity and darkneſs. I avow it, Shepherd, I avow it, and to make you avow the ſame, ſuffer that I make you ſee that, which without doubt, you remember not to have ſeen, I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50736:6"/>would ſay, the Riſing and the Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Sun in our Campaigns, be it when we are in our Woods, or when we walk on the Banks of ſome of our Rivers: Ah, Shepherd! if it is true, that fine Objects ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the Spirit, and that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Jaſper, Porphyry, Pearls, Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds and Gold, give agreeable thoughts, what ought not this fair Star to do, at his Arrival upon the Horizon? He who hath communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to all theſe things the little Beauty that they have? In fine, there, is nothing more Beautiful in all the Univerſe, than his Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent entrance in the Mornings with us; at <hi>Rome,</hi> they ſcarce ever ſee him without Clouds; the Miſts and the Smoke obſcure one part of his Rays; and they ſay, he is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry not to be employed in that place, but to enlighten Cheats, Flatterers, and voluntary Slave, they think (I ſay) that he hides one part of his Light, becauſe his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50736:6"/>heat ſerves not there, but to dry the Dirt in the Streets. In the place where we are, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to appear, it is but to diſſipate the innocent Vapors which ariſe out of the Earth, and to dry the Dew which refreſhes our Fields, and to open our Roſes, to paint the Wings of our Butterflies, and to receive the Vows of all the Shepherds in our Hamlets; alſo he appeareth to us all the Day, with ſo much magnificence, as nothing can equal his Glory: the firſt of his Rayes begin to ſow Purple, Gold, and Azure, in ſome paths of the Sky, and it ſeemeth that all Nature rejoyceth therein. The darkneſs of the Night diſſipates it ſelf, the Stars diſappear by Reſpect, the Birds awake themſelves to ſing: Our Flocks would go out of the Folds, and all our Shepherds and Shepherdeſſes, who are never wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſeeing the ſame Object, when 'tis agreeable, admire more and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50736:7"/>more, this marvellous Maſs of rich and vivid Colors, which ſpread themſelves upon the Clouds at the arrival of this fair Star: they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, I ſay, theſe Beautiful Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Light, which he communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates to all Objects which are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to receive it. He gilds the tops of our Mountains, and ſilvers the ſurface of our Rivers, and by his long luminous Beams he pierceth through the ſhades of our Foreſts, only to render 'em more agreeable, and not to take away their cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nor to diſſipate their ſhade. In the morning he permits us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him, at Noon it ſuffices that our Groves defend us from his Heat; in the Evening he makes us ſee his Image in our Fountains; but ſo charming and ſo marvellous, as all the Diamonds in the World cannot equal the Beauty of the leaſt of his Rayes. When he leads away the day, he gives us hope to ſee him very ſoon again, by the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perb
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50736:7"/>Apparel which goes before him, and when he unrobes himſelf, he ſeems to aſſure us, by the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Riches that he hath employ'd to paint the Skies, of Vermillion, and of burniſh'd Gold, and that pleaſing variety of bright and dark Colors, that his abſence ſhall not be long, and that he will return again to us in a few hours, as illuſtrious as before. I avow, Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, by this feeble Diſcourſe that I am about to make, that there is nothing at <hi>Rome</hi> ſo fine as this that I have now repreſented to you, though this is not the onely thing that renders our Abode agreeable. There are other places where the Sun ſcarce enters, which are yet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting enough; We have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Grots within the Concavity of Rocks, where the Day never comes without difficulty, and the Night mingles its Shades with the Light, though Darkneſs is never intirely baniſh'd thence, and, tho'
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50736:8"/>they are carpetted and hung but with Moſs, nevertheleſs the Silence and the Coolneſs that's there is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver encountred but with Pleaſure: there one may Treat himſelf with that Tranquillity and that Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as if he were the onely thing in Nature; there one may peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably rejoyce of all the Charmes of Solitude: You may, if you pleaſe, go from hence to a Fountain, the Waters whereof are ſo clear, that it permits you to ſee through its Waves the diverſity of the Flints and Gravel which are at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of its Bed: It makes but a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble murmur, apter to invite you to repoſe, than to diſturb you with Chagrin: the Waters which flow from it forms a Brook, which winds it ſelf like a Serpent, making a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle noiſe as it paſſes amongſt the Peebles, the Moſs, and the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, into a Medow, where 'tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with others which run thither, and there unite and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50736:8"/>their Waters, till they make a large River, whereof the flowing and the Banks make a new Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the Purity on't ought, without doubt, to be more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able than the muddy Waters of <hi>Tiber.</hi> But if from theſe peaceable Beauties you'll paſs to thoſe which mingle their Charms with I know not what of terrible, and which give ſomewhat of Horror in divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: We have dreadful Precipices, we have Rocks whoſe Tops touch the Clouds, and from whence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend furious Torrents, who in their fall make as much Noiſe as Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or the Sea: They ſay theſe are Mountains of Snow, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate themſelves one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, 'till ſo many Waters ruſh from 'em, that one would ſay to ſee 'em <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oul and bound in ſuch abundance, and with ſuch impetuoſity, that they would ſubmerge all the Earth, nevertheleſs they fall into a Gulph which is at the foot of a Rock,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50736:9"/>from whence they go till they hide themſelves in the Abyſs, where they go (without doubt) to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Tribute to thoſe from whence they came. At parting from hence, Shepherd, will you that I conduct you into one of theſe fine Medows, where you ſhall find a great Carpet of different flowers, where you may ſee an hundred Sources of Chryſtal; where on the one ſide there is an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able River, on the other a great quantity of Pines, Willows, and Alders, who by their ſhade permit you to paſs the Day (though the Sun be intirely there) very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly, as well as the Shepherds which repoſe themſelves there; but perhaps you will not ſtay there any long time: Let us go then, Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, let us go into one of theſe Foreſts, whereof the Obſcurity, the Silence, and the Age ſeem to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print a Reſpect in all thoſe which walk there. If this ſhady Foreſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50736:9"/>were at the Gates of <hi>Rome,</hi> it would not but be fill'd with Thieves or fugitive Criminals: and in this place, here with us, is found but Deer, Stags, Hinds and Kids: You may know by their number, that we employ not often the Toils to take 'em, and you may ſee by the little care they take to hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that this place is an inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Azile unto 'em. All theſe great Paths, where the Day per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits us with difficulty to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the Colors, and we almoſt doubt whether the Leaves be not rather Blue than Green, leaves us not without ſomething wherewith to divert the Spirit, and the Eyes of a Melancholy Shepherd, and in ſome of the Walks, that have leſs of this thick ſhade, where the Sun-Beams come to diſſipate a part of this agreeable Night, there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any thing ſeen finer than theſe long ſtreams of Silver, who ſeem as they would force this Obſcurity
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50736:10"/>to yield its place to their Light, and one would ſay, by the Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Leaves, that they would preſs themſelves together to hinder their paſſage, but it makes
'em tremble the more, to give entrance to this Enemy of Darkneſs. As you walk from this Foreſt, will you let me conduct you to the ſide of a great Pond, whereof the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity wants little of the place from whence you came (which ſtay'd you to remark its Beauties.) The Zephire here is no more than what ſerves to curl its Waves, and it agitates them ſo gently, as you may eaſily ſee all the Fiſh which are at the bottom of theſe Waters, which are as Clear as Peaceable; ſome of 'em ſwim with precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſeek their Food, others elevate themſelves above the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whilſt ſome of the more fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful go to hide themſelves at the leaſt Noiſe that they underſtand. But, if from the bottom of this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50736:10"/>Chryſtal, you will conſider the Surface, you ſhall ſee it all cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Swans; you may admire, Shepherd, the whiteneſs of their Plumage, the Gravity that they obſerve in ſwimming, and the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pride which appears in their Eyes: Say they not that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe all thoſe who behold 'em? and ſay they not alſo, that they have hovers in which they have a deſign to pleaſe, when they make Sayls of their Wings, to divert 'em, and that they ſwim not but to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd? Ah, Sheph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d! how far are the Inhabitants of <hi>Rome</hi> from theſe innocent pleaſures? their tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Life robs 'em of theſe Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacies. I am not yet at the end of the deſcription of the Places where we inhabit, I muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conduct you upon one of theſe high Mountains, from whence you may diſcover at once Rivers, Forreſts, Plains, and Paſturage; whereof the view is ſo boundleſs,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50736:11"/>as if the Objects ſeemed to efface and ſhut up themſelves, and, as if the Sky touch'd the fartheſt part of the Earth you deſcry. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you love not a Proſpect ſo extenſive: Suffer then that I bring you to ſome of our little Hills, or into ſome of our Valleys, to the end to make you avow, that their Abundance ought to be preferred to the Sterility of the ſeven Hills of <hi>Rome:</hi> Theſe little Corners of the Earth are ſo much favoured of Heaven, that they ſeem to be intirely covered from all the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Air: The Wind ſeldom blows, the Hail ſpoileth not the Grapes, the Verdure is eternal there; and, I think, what they cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate not, the Sun onely does it, and makes 'em grow and ripen, and does all that which Agricul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture produces elſewhere with ſo much care and pain. And, not to forget that which ſhews the Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of our Shepherds, and that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50736:11"/>which is the innocent Love of our Shepherdeſſes; Can you put in compariſon the Perfumes at <hi>Rome</hi> with the amiable Odor of our Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, Roſes, and Gilli-flowers, there is at leſt this difference, that the one ſatisfies but the Senſe of Smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and the other, beſides their agreeable Odour, pleaſe the Sight infinitely; in effect, can you ſee any thing finer than this prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Quantity of Flowers where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our Gardens are repleniſh'd, be it for their Form, for their love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhining Colors, or for that pleaſing Variety that's found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt 'em. Believe me, Shepherd, the Magnificent Tapiſtries of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhews you nothing ſo marvellous: the Purple in them is not ſo fair as the incarnat of our Roſes, the Pearls of our Crowns Imperial, are better than thoſe of the Orient, and the leaſt of our Flowers is more worthy of Admiration, than all that which Humane Art can invent.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50736:12"/>After that I have made you ſee that which I call the chief Work of the Sun, let me conduct you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the next Grove, it is there where you ſhall find that which one can never find at <hi>Rome;</hi> it is there, where you ſhall underſtand what they never underſtood in any City; it is there that you ſhall be conſtrain'd to avow, that one muſt be inſenſible of Pleaſure, not to prefer the Countrey Life to that of the Court. See then, I conjure you, this great, number of Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds and Shepherdeſſes, who, whilſt the great Heat of the Day continues, have conducted their Flocks to graze in the ſhadow, under the thickeſt part of the Grove, and admire the good meen of the one, and the Beauty of the other, (though this is not yet the place where I ought to ſpeak of it) and hear onely that which they hear, (I would ſay) this great quantity of Birds, who, by their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50736:12"/>different Notes make ſuch an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able conſort: They ſay to thoſe that underſtand their Songs, that they diſpute amongſt themſelves who ſhall carry the prize of the Victory. But, above the reſt, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire this knowing Maſter of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, who, by the leaſt of his Songs ſurmounts all others; the reſt have a ſenſe of their feebleneſs, and they refrain by impuiſſance, or by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and the Nightingales are thoſe onely which come with equal Arms, and aſſay to vanquiſh or to be overcome, the one of the other. Hear how admirably this here paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his Cadences, how he falls his Voice and upholds it again, and inforces it there, and with what juſtneſs he animates his Songs: He who anſwers him hath a particular Charm, he is more languiſhing and more Amorous; but as he is more feeble than the other, I think he will be overcome: Hear how they redouble their Efforts, you may
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50736:13"/>diſcern the Joy in him who find, himſelf to have the Advantages and the Dolor, and the Anger of it, in him who feels his Forces di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh. Behold, Shepherd, when he can no more, his paſſages are no leſs juſt, though they're more frequent; the ſweetneſs of his Voice changeth it ſelf, and he ſings no more but by Deſpair; I diſcern through the traverſe of theſe leaves, his Feet can no more embrace the Branch that upholds him, and I ſee him fall with deſpight, and in falling he yet murmurs ſome lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Notes, and he had almoſt rather loſe his life then his voice. Behold, Shepherd the only Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Campaigns, and compare it (I conjure you) wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h that at <hi>Rome:</hi> Though the condition of this poor Bird be worthy of Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I avow 'tis better that Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on make Nightingals dye, than that it ſhould Reverſe Thrones and Empires. In ſumm Shepherd, It is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50736:13"/>not only in the Spring, the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and the Autumne, that we have the advantage of the City; the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as dreadful, and as Horrid as it is deciph'red, hath ſomething a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt its Rigors, of fine and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent, in our Campaigns; The Snow which in the City loſes all its Whiteneſs as it falls, and conceives it there only on the tops of the Houſes; It makes here Rich Plumes with with the Branches of our Cypreſs, of our Cedars and of our Firs; Theſe Trees (I ſay) of whom the leaves fall not, mingles their verdure, with its Whiteneſs, and, makes without doubt ſuch an agreeable object, as the Summer cannot ſhow us: and when the Ice, and ſharpneſs of our Froſts have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted all our Rivers, into Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal, we ſee all our Trees Loaden with Diamonds; But you'll ſay to me perhaps that theſe Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds enrich us not, and that the Sun takes from us, what the Cold
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50736:14"/>hath given us: But Shepherds if theſe Diamonds, enrich us not, at leaſt they do not make us Criminals, we cannot ſuborn the fidelity of any perſon with 'em, neither can they be employed to ſo many ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did uſes, as (you know) they do theirs at <hi>Rome.</hi> There is yet one thing in the City, which ſeemeth to me inſupportable, it is that they ſay there, that there is but one ſeaſon in the year, for thoſe who inhabit in't: They ſee always the ſame things, they have always the ſame employments, their Houſes are always alike, their Pleaſures change not, and unleſs they have Cold, and Heat, according to the divers temperature of the Air, there arrives no change in their Life: On the Contrary with us, to whom Nature renews the year four times, giving us ſeveral em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys, very different: The Spring with her Chaplet of Flowers, calls us to the care of our Medows
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50736:14"/>and our Flocks; The Summer Crowned with Wheat-Ears, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges us to the care of our Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſts: The Autumn with her Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of Vine-Branches, would not that we ſhould leave our Grapes to be ſpoiled by paſſengers: The Winter covered with Ice, would have us render to the Earth, that Tribute that each one owes her, to the end that at another time, ſhe may reſtore with Uſury, the Grain that we have Sown in her boſome, O! Shepherd how inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent is this Uſury? and how unlike to that which is practiſed in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? we impoveriſh no perſon to enrich our ſelves, of this ſort; we need not hide the gain that is got in this manner, they can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther envy nor reproach us, neither accuſe us of any Crime: For as much as the more careful we are, the more we are praiſed. In the other, all their cares are blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, if they are not blam'd, they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50736:15"/>have more pain, and leſs trouble, and which they acquire by inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, they cannot poſſeſs but with inquietude: They fear the envious, their Enemies, and Thieves: But for us, we have neither Enviors, Enemies, nor we fear no other Thieves, then the poor Birds, which Robus of ſome of our Fruits, however we would not baniſh from our Campaigns, theſe innocent Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals, for the diverſion they give us in other incounters. But to make you ſee that maugre the Magnificent Structure of your Temples and of your Palaces, that notwithſtanding the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Jaſper, the Porphyry, that make all their Ornaments: and maugre your Aquaeducts, your Statutes, and triumphant Arches; we are the more veritable poſſeſſors of all the faireſt gifts of Nature you have not. But to remark, that <hi>Rome</hi> Adorns not her ſelf, but with that which the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50736:15"/>Earth ſhuts in her Boſome, and of that which ſhe hides from the Eyes of men: Here we rejoyce of of all that, with which ſhe Adorns her ſelf, and of all which ſhe ſends forth to the view of the Univerſe. No Shepherd, theſe are not her Treaſures, theſe Mettalls, which are at this Day, the Tirants of Spirits, and the Corrupters of the moſt Sage; If they were her riches, we ſhould ſee our Trees loaden with Gold, Pearls, and Jewels, ſhe would adorn her ſelf, with her faireſt Ornaments and not leave imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that which you call her chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Works; we ſhould not need Lapidaries, to Cut and Embe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh our Diamonds, nor Refiners to purifie Gold, nor Artiſts to poliſh our Pearls, all theſe things would be finiſht before they are ſeen and produced, in perfection, as are our Flowers, our Woods, and our Fountains. Ceaſe then Shepherd, Ceaſe to remember,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50736:16"/>that the Abode of <hi>Rome</hi> is finer than that of our Campaigns, and prepare you at laſt to make the magnificence of your diverſions at <hi>Rome,</hi> to give place to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence of ours: Of all the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Feaſts with which you have entertained me, thoſe of the Triumphs, and thoſe of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates of your Gladiators, are the moſt Celebrated. But O! <hi>Tytirus,</hi> theſe Feaſts, and theſe Joys, have ſomewhat of Tyranique, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt; and it is difficult, for Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional perſons to rejoyce, in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many infortunates. That which is called Delight, ought not to be mingled with Bitterneſs; Tears and Laughter, ought not to be ſeen together: And Blood ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ought not to pleaſe, even in Battles; much leſs in Diverſions. Nevertheleſs the moſt agreeable that they have at <hi>Rome,</hi> are to ſee Kings in Chains, and four thouſand Gladiators killing one
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50736:16"/>another, to pleaſe the Roman people: O! Shepherd what are thoſe people who divert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſeeing Rivers of Blood, and Mountains of the Dead. For us, we afflict our ſelves when one of our Lambs are Sick; and we are far from rejoyceing to ſee the miſerable dye cruelly: neither does it ſatisfie us, to behold Kings, or Princes loaden with Chains: For me, Shepherd; if I ſee ſuch a ſpectacle I have more compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the vanquiſht, than eſteem for the Victors. And in fine (to ſpeak to you as I think) I ſee no Innocent pleaſure at <hi>Rome.</hi> They inſult there upon the infortunate, and there they make their unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſlaves periſh: They lead thither in Chains Captive Kings, after they have Uſurped their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms: And they hear there, and behold, not only without horror, but with ſatisfaction, the laſt plaints and actions of the dying.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50736:17"/>
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> (as they ſay) wept after the Battle of <hi>Pharſaliae,</hi> over the great number of the ſlain, that he ſaw lying there, without life and motion. But at <hi>Rome</hi> they Laugh at that which made Him weep; And they call that a Feaſt of rejoyceing, which ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be named a publique mourning. Behold then Shepherd (I conjure you) if we are cruel, or innocent in our joys: And if in making you remember it, you avow not, that if we have leſs Pompe, we have more Ingenuity, and more Addreſs, more Equity, and more pleaſure: Recall then to your imagination one of the general Feaſts of our Hamlets, or one of the Sacrifices that we make to the Gods, after the ingather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Harveſts: is there any thing more agreeable then to ſee not Kings loaden with Fetters; not Gladiators covered with Blood and Wounds; But an innumerable
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50736:17"/>company of Shepherds, and Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdeſſes Crown'd with Chaplets of Flowers with a joy in their Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages which communicates its ſelf to all thoſe that behold 'em: Some with Flagelets, others, with Shalms, ſome lead the Victims, others bring the Conſecrated Vaſes, ſome raiſe the Altar of Turfe, others put fire to it: And almoſt all have their Crooks enriched with Devices, Cyphers and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and the propriety of their Habits, ſerves to render them more aimable: It is not gorgious, but it is graceful, and although nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Purple, nor Precious-Stones glitter in them; yet their white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the beautiful variety of the Jewels that the Spring, Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and Autumn gives us, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently repairs that defect. In ſumm Shepherd, the beauty of my Companions (if I deceive not my ſelf) ought not to yeild to that of the Roman Dames. You will anſwer
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:50736:18"/>perhaps, if it be true that they have as fine features, and an Air as agreeable, yet I cannot deny, but that the Sun-burning in the Country, ſpoils their complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and deſtroys much of its freſhneſs; But beſides that the thickneſs of our Shades, defends us from that Enemy; I have yet to ſay that Tanning is better then Painting, and a native beauty is more charming, than that which is Artificial. For us, Shepherd, we appear ſuch as we are; we have no other mirors, than our Fountains, nor other Paint then the Dew: Nevertheleſs there are maids found amongſt us, in our Woods, whoſe complexions are ſo marvelous that they ſurpaſs the Lillies, in whiteneſs and the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt incarnate of the Roſes. The modeſty of their Actions, the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of their diſcourſes, and the ſerenity which appears in their Eyes are things which are are not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50736:18"/>found but in our Campaigns, elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where they are but faint and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial: They regard, but to be regarded, they make no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts without deſign; and that is not fine which appears ſo: And they ſometimes deceive the diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perſons. But to return Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, to this fair Aſſembly, where our ſage Paſtors, are the Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the Judges of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, who have prepared the Prize for the Victors, (in this Feaſt) you know well by the ſimplicity of their Matter, that it is no ſentiment of avarice, that gives 'em the deſire to gain 'em, ſince that are deſtined for Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, (as you know better than I) are but Panniers of Reeds, Sheep-hooks, Flagalets, Shalms and Darts: And for the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdeſſes, Baskets of Ruſh, Crowns of Flowers, Noſegays and Ribands: Nevertheleſs we have as much care to vanquiſh,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50736:19"/>as if we acted to Conquer all the Earth. But Shepherd, we need no Arms to carry this Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory; we ſhed no Blood to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat our Enemies: They lead not in triumph, thoſe who have had the diſadvantage; on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, inſtead of inchaining them, they embrace 'em, and they ſay to 'em, that they are the moſt expert, tho' they are not the moſt fortunate: And laſtly they ſeek to comfort 'em of this little diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace; (and if I am not very much deceived) Races, Lutes, Dancing, Muſick and Poetry, give more diverſion than all the Combates of the Gladiators; He then that Runs the Swifteſt: He who Plays well on the Lute: He that Dances agreeably: He who makes the fineſt Verſe: And he who Sings moſt skilfully, gives, without doubt, more ſatisfaction than the Combates of Panthers and Tigers, whereof you make
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50736:19"/>ſo much diſcourſe. Think Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, think well: If you had not rather ſee the Shepherdeſs <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea</hi> Dance, or the fair <hi>Lycoris</hi> Sing; than to ſee a Lyon devour a Tiger, or an Elephant overthrow a <hi>Rhinorceros:</hi> Yes you like it better, I remark enough upon your Viſage that you accord with what I ſay, and I think alſo that you love better to ſee theſe two fair Maids tho' they have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enthralled you, than to be the ſpectator of the moſt magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Triumph, that <hi>Rome</hi> hath ever made you ſee, when <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> himſelf was Victorious. Bluſh not Shepherd at this little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach that I make you, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of ſo many Verſes that you have compoſed for their Glory; neither be aſhamed of having car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed the prize ſo often at our exerciſes, from the expert <hi>Melibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> from the active <hi>Coridon,</hi> from the hardy <hi>Menalcus,</hi> and from the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50736:20"/>ingenious <hi>Daphnies,</hi> in the ſight of our moſt knowing Shepherds. But if from our publick Feaſts, you will paſs to thoſe innocent Wars, which make ſome of our greateſt pleaſures, I would ſay Fiſhing, and Hunting, you will be conſtrained to avow, that <hi>Rome</hi> knows not all that which is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to pleaſe, ſince ſhe cannot give theſe agreeable diverſions, to thoſe which inhabit in her: Nevertheleſs it is certain that one cannot find any thing more likely to pleaſe, than to ſee many Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdeſſes, with their Lines in their hands, keeping all a moſt profound ſilence, for fear leſt by the noiſe they ſhould make the Fiſh that they would take, goe from 'em, and hide themſelves in the bottom of the Waters: The one makes her Fiſh-hooks ready upon the Banks: Another caſt her Line into the River, and is ſo attentive to what ſhe does,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50736:20"/>that ſhe appears to be her own ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, &amp; by an action as ſubtil as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, lifts up her Arms, draws the Line, and overjoyed with her prize, caſts the Fiſh on the Banks, which after bowing, raiſing, and divers boundings, makes the emraulds of the Medow, ſhine with his Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Scales. Another hoping to have the ſame ſucceſs as her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, draws her Line without catching any thing; wherewith others hold themſelves comforted, in having the ſame deſtiny. But that which is moſt diverting, is to ſee our Shepherds loaden with Nets, go to Fiſh a Pond; it is there that when they are happy, they make to be ſeen, in drawing their Net, a living wave as it comes upon the ſhore, by the multitude and diverſity of the Fiſh, that, they have taken: ſome leap above the Nets, others Break 'em, ſome bound above the Vaſe; others more happy ſave themſelves, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50736:21"/>others intangle themſelves more in ſeeking to be diſengaged, and all of
'em make their efforts to ſave their lives, and to eſcape from that which retains 'em: But 'tis in vain that they ſtrive, and beat themſelves, for they have chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their element, and they muſt dye, the coolneſs of the Graſs is not for them, like that of the Water. This diverſion tho' very ſimple is not always ſo; ſince Queens as well as Shepherdeſſes, have ſometimes imployed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in't: And <hi>Cleopatra</hi> who had the Glory to take, in her Nets, the Hearts of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony,</hi> affected to go a Fiſhing, and to caſt the Line, and made it one of her moſt ordinary Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. But Shepherd, if there be ſome pleaſure in deceiving the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence of Fiſhes, there is no leſs in deceiving that of the Birds, As ſoon as they have hid that which is to take 'em, under the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50736:21"/>heaps of Corn, that they have caſt 'em to the end that in ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſomewhat to live, they find wherewith to dye; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they Shoot 'em, ſometimes they are ſurpriſed upon the Trees where they uſe to go, the Branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es thereof being full of ſome kind of Bird-lime, which retains 'em ſo faſt by the Wings, that the more they endeavour to fly from 'em, the more they are intangled in theſe dangerours Branches. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe innocent exerciſes, be it Fiſhing or Hunting, you ſhall ſee the one, and the other, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning charged with their priz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; the Shepherds carrying great Panniers of Reed, full of Fiſh; the Shepherdeſſes bringing Cages of Ruſh, where they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved alive ſome Birds, that have pleaſed 'em; and altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out abandoning the care of their Flocks, retake the way of their Cabanes. Thoſe that have been
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50736:22"/>happy, tho' charged with their booty, leave not to ſing ſome Eglogue, or to play on their Shalms; all their Flocks following their Maſters or their Miſtreſſes: The Dogs by their fidelity, take heed that neither Ewe, nor Lambe go a ſtray; and the Bulls by their long cries; and by their Bellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, advertiſe thoſe of the Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, that the Hunting or the Fiſhing is ended; and they come with all imaginable impreſſions of joy, to know the ſucceſs. It is too much Shepherd, it is too much, that I ſpeak of this innocent Warr, although (if I be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) it ought to be preferred to that which has made to be erected, the moſt ſuperb Trophies and wherewith the Victors, have obtained their moſt magnificent Triumphs. Come then if you pleaſe to ſomwhat more ſolid, and let us compare the Vices of <hi>Rome,</hi> to the Vertues that are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50736:22"/>to be ſeen amongſt us. In the firſt place <hi>Rome</hi> is repleniſht with Flatterers, and we ſcarce know what Flatterie is: At <hi>Rome</hi> Lying and Wickedneſs Reigns, and in our Woods there always appears Verity: They are never wanting to praiſe that which meriteth to be praiſed: At <hi>Rome</hi> all men are ſlaves, either to their ambition, or to their avarice, and in our Campaigns, we poſſeſs more Gods then we deſire to have, and are avaricious but of time only, which we would always employ well. There men found at <hi>Rome,</hi> which make the greateſt poiſons in Nature, their greateſt treaſures, with which they would deſtroy their Enemies, (or themſelves if it happen that they are to be puniſht for their offences) Amongſt us we make ſalutary herbs our deareſt treaſures, which can heal the ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and biteing of Serpents. At <hi>Rome</hi> they think but of their own intereſt, here we think but of our
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50736:23"/>pleaſure, provided it be innocent: At <hi>Rome</hi> all thoſe that inhabit there, ſeek how they may Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves acceptable to the Prince: In our Woods we ſeek but our Equals: At <hi>Rome</hi> they will not be free, but love to kiſs the hand which enchains
'em: in our Hamlets we pay obedience to our Old Paſtors, with as much affection as freedom. At <hi>Rome</hi> thoſe who make the Laws, deride and break 'em; with us the moſt ſage Shepherds inſtruct us rather by their example, than by their words; yes we do rather what they do, than what they ſay; and we know not amongſt us, thoſe that break either Laws, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms. At <hi>Rome</hi> riches only make the difference between men; with us 'tis vertue and merit, make the diſtinction. At <hi>Rome</hi> all are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied either to deceive others, or to hinder themſelves from being deceived; in the place where we
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50736:23"/>are, we ſeek but the occaſion to ſerve one another; if it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen at any time, that one of our Shepherdeſſes loſe a Sheep from her Flock, that ſhe loves better than the reſt, all our Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds are in pain till ſhe recover that which ſhe hath loſt; They inform themſelves with care, and they tell to all they meet, all the marks of this aimable Animal, to the end to know whether they have ſeen it; they deſcribe its Whiteneſs, its Marks, the Flowers and the Ribands, which are tied to its Horns, and forget nothing of all that which may ſerve to their deſign; and if they are hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py enough to retrive it, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn with as much joy as one of your Conſuls when they have gained a Battail. It is true that we ardently love to ſerve, not only our friends, but all thoſe that have any need of us. At <hi>Rome</hi> it is not ſo, for all the world there,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50736:24"/>rejoyces at the misfortunes of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Thoſe whom the Prince looketh not on with a good Eye, are abandoned of thoſe that they have the moſt obliged; whatever vertue they have on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, thoſe that he favoureth, tho' they ſhould be the moſt vicious, and the moſt imperfect of men, are found to have not only friends, but alſo Idolaters and Slaves. It goes not in this manner in our Campaigns; we ſee nothing above us but the Heavens: We have no Princes, nor favorites to fear or ſeek for; we live with Equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we love thoſe which love us, and we hate no perſon. In ſumm, I have always heard ſay, that Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hards were the Image of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, and that they ought to govern their People, as we go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern our Flocks, and that the Scepter and Sheep-hook ought to have the ſame reſemblance. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs of the Faſhion that theſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:50736:24"/>things are recounted, there is a notable difference between 'em, or to ſay better, they have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, we love our Flock with tenderneſs, we have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther care but this to render them happy, we chuſe the freſheſt Graſs for 'em, and the cleareſt Water, we give 'em a faithful and couragious Guard, which are our Dogs, and we defend 'em our ſelves at the hazard of our Lives, when the Woolves attaque 'em, and we take care not only to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and defend 'em, but to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der 'em from the extremities, of Cold and Heat, in the Winter we leave 'em in the Sheep-folds when the Froſt has Iced the Graſs. In the Scorching Heat of Summer, we ſeek umbrages in our Groves for 'em and defend 'em from all ſorts of inconveniencies: when they are ſick we ſeek remedies which are proper for 'em; when they are well, we deck them with
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50736:25"/>Flowers, and Ribands; it is not not ſo With ſome of theſe Princes who ought to be Paſtors, they do not love their Flock, nor care to be loved of 'em, provided that they be feared, they ſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more of the Crook to fear 'em than to reaſſemble or defend 'em; inſtead of chuſing their Graſs and their Waters, they would have their Flock ſerve only to their magnificence and profit; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of keeping 'em as we do, they reverſe the order, and 'tis the Flock which keep the Paſtors; in leiv (I ſay) of defending 'em, from all ſorts of incommodities, 'tis theſe that cauſe it every way, when they are ſick they are ſo far from ſeeking remedies, that they augment their Evils, by their tyranies; and when they are well, they are ſo far from adorning them, that they ſpoil them of their natural ornaments: we would have our Flocks always Fat, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50736:25"/>they would have theirs Lean and Feeble. Shepherd we content us to take from 'em their Wool to make afterwards Purple wherewith to make their moſt Rich Habits, they pluck it from theirs with violence, and I dare ſay, that the Purple that covers them, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Borrows its Color from the Blood of their Flock, than from the induſtry of the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Artiſts, of whom they boaſt ſo at <hi>Rome.</hi> Ah Shepherd, if we had ſuch Paſtors amongſt us, we would baniſh 'em from our Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagns, and we would eſteem 'em worſe than Wolves, who are the declared enemies of our Flocks: we would degrade 'em from this noble employ, and take a way their Sheep-hooks, Pipes, Scrips, Shalms, and all the Glorious marks of our innocent profeſſion. <hi>Tity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> I muſt tell you 'tis a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous thing, when a Soveraign is no good Paſtor, and it were
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50736:26"/>better to make a faithful Paſtor, a King, than to have a King, which cannot be a good Paſtor: I know what you will ſay to me, that there is to be found, at this time, a Prince who has ſo much ſweetneſs, clemency and bounty, that he rather merits the name of a good Paſtor, than that of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: And that <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> after having brought back his Troops, is one of the beſt Paſtors that ever carried Sheep-hook: But tell me in a few words, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sheepcotes hath he deſtroyed, and deſolated to inrich his Flock? how much Blood hath he ſhed? how many Paſtors hath he kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? how many Tigers, Panthers, and Wolves, have ſerved him, to make Deſart the faireſt Medow of the Empire? and how many innocent Lambs, have felt his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, before they found his Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency? Speak Shepherd I conjure you, and anſwer me preciſely.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:50736:26"/>No no, I ſee well by your ſilence, that you cannot contradict me, and that you are conſtrained to avow, that there are more Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors to be found, who would make good Princes, than Princes, capable to be good Paſtors. In effect, the felicity of a Compaign life, is not ſo very much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known at <hi>Rome,</hi> but that it hath been embraced with fervor, by her moſt illuſtrious Heroes; yes thoſe who after having gain'd Battails, (as you know better than I) have Cultivated the Earth with their own hands, they have alſo, in the preſſing affairs of the publick, been recalled from holding the Plow to guide the Reigns of the Empire, and from the Coulter, to the head of an Army; and from Solitude to Court. Nevertheleſs theſe men, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have done theſe great and fair Actions there, have never been more praiſed, than when af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50736:27"/>having governed the repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, carried Cities with force, gained Battails, recovered the Bounds of Roman Puiſſance, and meritted the Honors of Triumph, they were ſeen to refuſe theſe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, to return to the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Plow, from the head of an Army to the Campaign life, and from the Court to ſolitude. After this Shepherd, complain not of your deſtiny, and have not the injuſtice, to find nothing ſweet but the magnificences of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince our ſimplicity is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than her Artifice; and if from general manners, we paſs to particular paſſions, you ſhall find that all thoſe which have been accuſtomed, to cauſe the greateſt diſorders, are not known amongſt us, to produce any other than agreeable effects. Firſt ambition torments us not, we are but the Children of Shepherds, and we would be no more; our deſire
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50736:27"/>having no other object, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing elſe, we live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pride, and without inquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; we ſee nothing above our heads, but the Heavens, nor nothing under us: We are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inſolence, and without cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grin, and we would not change our Sheep-hooks, for all the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the univerſe. It is eaſy to Judge that if we are not Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, we know neither envy, nor avarice, ſince theſe two paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, are almoſt inſeperable one from another: wrath is unknown to us, and hatred can have no entrance in a Country where all is worthy to be loved: but you'll ſay to me what then is this paſſion, which hath been accuſtomed to produce ſuch ſtrange diſorders in the City, and of which you'll make but agreeable effects to be ſeen in your Campaigns? As for me there is ſo long a time ſince I dwelt there, that I have almoſt loſt the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50736:28"/>Remembrance on't. It is <hi>Tityrus</hi> the moſt noble, and the moſt puiſſant of all others, it is that which made <hi>Hercules</hi> Spin, which Burnt <hi>Troy,</hi> and which hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown ſo many Empires; which hath cauſed ſo many Ruins, through all the Corners of the Earth; which hath made ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wars; which hath given <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> to <hi>Cleopatra, Auguſtus</hi> to <hi>Livia:</hi> It is, in fine, this paſſion, which hath its birth amongſt the delicacies of Flowers, of Groves, of Fountains, of Medows, of Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, and Shepherdeſſes, with more innocence and leſs bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, than upon the Throne, and in the Palaces of great Kings, it is in thoſe elevated places, that this Paſſion called Love, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt always dangerous: a lover which gives Laws to all the World, is no leſs apt to receive it of his Miſtreſs: He wills what
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50736:28"/>He deſires more ardently, and obſtinately, than others, and when He finds any obſtacle in his deſigns, this Crowned ſlave, that hath not been accuſtomed to obey, and who hath always been accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be obeyed by all thoſe who approach him; This ſlave (I ſay) quits his Chains and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volts, remounts upon the Throne, and becomes the Tyrant of her, of whom he called himſelf the Captive, and often makes her prove the moſt funeſt adventures. But on the contrary amongſt us, this little God, whoſe puiſſance hath no bounds, never appears in our Woods, without the Graces of his Mother, he inſpires not into the hearts of Shepherds, none but reaſonable ſentiments, we ſee 'em kiſs their Fetters, even then when the Rigor of their Miſtreſſes, makes 'em ſeem heavieſt, They receive favors with Tranſport, and when that they are ill treated, their
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:50736:29"/>diſcretion and their patience, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges 'em, to ſupport this misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune with reſpect; and with ſubmiſſion: They are always our Slaves and by conſequence they are never our Tyrants: we have ſome rigorous Shepherdeſſes, but we have no indiſcreet Shepherds: They are in pain but to diſcover their plaints upon their Pipes, and their Shalms: their Verſe, their Song, and their diſcourſe, are all full of our praiſes; all our Trees are graven with then Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, and ours mingled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and by all their Actions, they give us dayly new marks of their eſteem, or Love. Conſtancy, that vertue which ſo few men practice in Cities, is incountred almoſt every where amongſt us: the equality of our Conditions, and of our Riches, make the moſt feeble to continue conſtant. There is here neither Scepters, Gold, or Diamonds, which may Blind or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50736:29"/>Suborne us; the wiſeſt amongſt us deſpiſe 'em and others know 'em not. You cannot ſee here a Husband repudiate many Wives, as at <hi>Rome;</hi> here the Lover con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues his paſſion after Mariage; he would not acquire us, but to eſteem us the more. Here they take care of the conqueſts that they have made and make it their Glory to carry but one Chain in all their life. Our Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdeſſes are no leſs faithful, their freedome and their innocence, make 'em ſo candid, that they diſguiſe not their ſentiments: They are modeſt and ſincere, and if a little Jealouſie, maugre ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vertues, which ought to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its birth, trouble not the tranquillity of our Woods, all our Roſes would be without Thorns, and our pleaſures without any mixture of Bitterneſs: However this Paſſion acts not here as at <hi>Rome,</hi> they have there recourſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50736:30"/>to violence, they put in uſe Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Poniards, and they ſerve 'em equally againſt the Rival, and the Miſtreſs. But here the greateſt evil which can arrive to us, is to ſee the complexion of our fair maids become a little Pale. The flocks or our Shepherds reſent the inquietudes of their maſters, who paſs their trouble in the darkeſt Groves, abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, to the care of one of their friends: This retreat how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever lets us ſee but few Tragical events, and ordinarily ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, ſome Song, and ſome Verſe make the Revenge and the accommodation of the moſt Jealous. If it is the Shepherdeſs which is irritated, they bring back her Lover to her feet, ſorrowful and changed as he is, She hears him, receives his juſtification; and if he be innocent ſhe pardons him, and if he be culpable, provided that he repent himſelf, and that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50736:30"/>he demand his Pardon with a good grace; but if, on the contrary, 'tis ſhe that is in the wrong, we condemn her to make him a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of Flowers, with her own hand, and ſomtimes we conſent that he Rob her of a Bracelet of her Hair; after that their felicity is more ſolidly founded than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and the Innocence of their lives juſtifies all their pleaſures, and they continue the moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of any in the World; the Shepherd takes care of his Miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Flock, and they are almoſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways upon the ſame heaths as his, they ſeek the ſame ſhades, their Sheep-hooks are engraven with the ſame Characters, their baskets are tied with the ſame Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans, their Sheep deck'd with the ſame colors, and even their Dogs ſeem to have contracted together ſome particular amity. This happy ſtate conſidered as it ought to be; is it not true Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50736:31"/>that the love at <hi>Rome,</hi> ought to be painted of another manner than our's? he ought to be repreſented as a Fury, and he ought to have more of the Bow, and more of the Flambo (given him) to ſee the diſorders that he hath cauſed, and he ought to bear a Syth as well as <hi>Saturn,</hi> and as death, ſince that he deſtroys as many, as Time and Death Deſtroy. He reverſeth all as well as they, he never carries Love into a Heart, but Hate, Jealouſie, and Choller, ſoon follow after it: He ought then to be depainted as a Monſter, he produceth ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny different things in the ſame moment. But for him who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habits, with us, he ought never to be ſeen but upon a Bank of Flowers; He ought to have his Wings of the ſame Colors as the Rain-Bow; and his Scarf, of the delicateſt Silk, his Shafts and Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver adorned with Roſes and Jaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50736:31"/>His complexion white and incarnate, that Laughter never abandon him, and that his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence appear in all his Actions, and that his Flambo ſeem rather to light us than to trouble us. Judge then (after all I have ſaid to you) if the abode at <hi>Rome,</hi> ought to be preferred to that of the Campaign? we have our habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in the fineſt places in Nature; we injoy all the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent pleaſures, and are the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of all veritable Riches, and we are not very far from the moſt ſolid vertue: our cuſtoms are equitable, and we have no Ambition, and we ſee nothing above us that we can deſire, and what can I ſay more? Render you then Shepherd, render you then to reaſon, to my prayers, and to my perſuations, and to your ſelf; for without doubt you would not indure, that I ſhould give you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50736:32"/>the Name of a Shep-herd, if you did not eſteem it glorious. So many Eglogues as you have made juſtifie (much better then I) the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of a Campaign life. Remember you no more than not to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of this that I deſire, It ſhall ſuffice one day to remember that <hi>Tityrus</hi> after having Sung the Acts of <hi>Aeneas</hi> (as he hath a deſign) hath not diſdain'd to accord his Pipe, and his Shalms, with thoſe of our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Shepherds: Remember not (I ſay) the Sunbeams to be as illuſtrious as I have depainted 'em; Nor our Rivers whoſe waves are Argent; Nor the aimable obſcurity of our Grots: Nor the Emraulds of our Medows: Nor our high Mountains, of whom the ſight is ſo delightfull: Nor our Torrents, the fall of whom tho' they are ſomewhat dreadful, are nevertheleſs diverting: Nor the Shades of our Forreſts: Nor of the Ponds covered with Swans: Nor our little Hills: Nor our Valleys:
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:50736:32"/>Nor the aimable diverſity of our Flowers: Nor our Woods: Nor the Muſick of our Nightingal: Nor the advantages that we have of the City in all the ſeaſons of the year: Forget alſo if you can the Beauty of our Shepherdeſſes: Loſe the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of our Feaſts, of our Sacrifices, of our Huntings, of our Fiſhings: The innocence of our manners, and of <hi>Amarillis</hi> her ſelf: But Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at leaſt to ſay nothing againſt a Campaign life. But go forth out of <hi>Rome</hi> and be as you were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: You have been a Shepherd, you have carryed the Sheep-hook and the Basket, with the ſame hand wherewith you have written the praiſes of a Trojan Prince, and the Complaints of <hi>Dido:</hi> You have writ the Plaints of <hi>Tityrus,</hi> to the Shepherdeſs <hi>Galatea,</hi> and the praiſes of a Campaign Life.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:50736:33"/>
               <head>The effect of this Harrangue.</head>
               <p>THE Reader may believe that this diſcourſe was perſuaſive, ſince that <hi>Virgil,</hi> (who is the ſame as <hi>Tityrus?</hi>) regretted not <hi>Rome,</hi> but once only, in all his Bucoliques (tho' he were three years in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them.) He imployed ſeven years afterwards, in the compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Georgicks, a work of the ſame nature, which contains all the Offices of a Paſtoral Life. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo can one (as I have ſaid) unleſs his imagination be deceived, but belive that <hi>Amarillis,</hi> perſuaded, in ſome ſort, <hi>Tityrus?</hi> This Large Campaign, is curiouſly enough de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>painted &amp; boldly enough touch'd, not to diſpleaſe his Eyes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:50736:33"/>
            <head>TO HER SELF On the COUNTREY.</head>
            <l>DOwn in the Countrey, far from Noiſe,</l>
            <l>Or ought that may diſturb its Joys;</l>
            <l>A Bower I have, near a young Grove,</l>
            <l>In which I live, as pleaſ'd as <hi>Jove.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In the firſt Age, when men were free.</l>
            <l>From Avarice, and Impiety:</l>
            <l>When little Cottages contain'd,</l>
            <l>Such <hi>Heroes,</hi> as o're many Raign'd,</l>
            <l>Their homely Couches often ſtood,</l>
            <l>Within a Gloomy Grot, or Wood.</l>
            <l>(Then happy Mortals did deſire,</l>
            <l>No more, than Nature did require,)</l>
            <l>Here I doe, pleaſantly ſurvay,</l>
            <l>In all her works, kind Nature's ſway,</l>
            <l>And find in every Roſe and Flow'r,</l>
            <l>Characters of a greater Pow'r.</l>
            <l>And have the pleaſures of the Spring,</l>
            <l>And flagrance of its Bloſſoming;</l>
            <l>And ſee how <hi>Flora</hi> does return,</l>
            <l>the favours of her love, the Sun</l>
            <l>How gay with Flow'rs ſhe does attire</l>
            <l>Herſelf, to highten his deſire.</l>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:50736:34"/>
            <l>Nor does ſhe only pleaſe the ſight,</l>
            <l>But Courts each others Appetite;</l>
            <l>With ſuch variety and ſtore;</l>
            <l>As Fate intended us no more:</l>
            <l>And by her bounty gives ſuch fruits,</l>
            <l>As even the niceſt Palate ſuits,</l>
            <l>Here's Real Lantskips to delight,</l>
            <l>And pleaſe my Fancy with their ſight:</l>
            <l>Here's Rocks, Rivers, and Woods Adorne</l>
            <l>The Feilds, their Mountains, Flocks &amp; Corne,</l>
            <l>And when I walk by Moſſy Springs,</l>
            <l>To hear their Gentle murmurings:</l>
            <l>I have the pleaſure of the Rare,</l>
            <l>And Cheap Muſicians of th' Aire.</l>
            <l>Theſe were the Joys, theſe were the ſights,</l>
            <l>In which of Old, were mens delights:</l>
            <l>Since Fate has me inſpir'd like thoſe,</l>
            <l>I will not this injoyment loſe;</l>
            <l>Not any thing ſhall me invite,</l>
            <l>To leave this innocent delight:</l>
            <l>Nor will I Quit this little Bow'r,</l>
            <l>To ſojourne with an Emperor.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:50736:34"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY ON <hi>Dramatick Poetry.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TIS not that I think my ſelf a competent Judge, even of the ſmalleſt matters, that are Tranſacted, that I adventure to declare my thoughts on this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Subject, (which deſerves a much better Pen) but only to intimate to my friends (to whom I am apt to ſcrible my thoughts) how great an inclination I have for this ingenious diverſion; of which ('thas been always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd,) a good uſe may be made, by intelligent perſons, who make reflections on what they either See or Read; for if they be inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:50736:35"/>to vertue, 'tis magnified upon the Theatre, and they incourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in't if to vice; 'tis there ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reprehended, and they may, if they will, be deter'd from it, by obſerving the puniſhment thereof in real, as well as feigned exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: (for uſually the Hiſtorical part of Tragedy is authentick.) And ſince I have begun to ſay ſomewhat of this kind of Poetry, I can't, without infinite ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to the Memory of thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent perſons, omit the firſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Maſters in't, of our Nation, Venerable <hi>Shakeſpear</hi> and the great <hi>Ben Johnſon:</hi> I have had a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular kindneſs always for moſt of <hi>Sakeſpear's</hi> Tragedies, and for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Comedies, and I can't but ſay that I can never enough admire his Stile (conſidering the time he writ in) and the great alteration that has been in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fineing of our Language ſince) for he has expreſſed himſelf ſo very
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:50736:35"/>well in't, that 'tis generally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd of ſtill; and for maintaining of the Characters of the perſons, deſign'd, I think none ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him; I ſhall ſay no more of <hi>Johnſon,</hi> but that his <hi>Catiline Sejanus,</hi> and <hi>Alchymiſt,</hi> will ſtand as eternal Monuments of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent abilities this way; but yet I confeſs I have a greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination for the incomparable of their time, <hi>Beavmont</hi> and <hi>Fletcher,</hi> and chiefly, of all theirs, for the <hi>Maid's Tragedy, King</hi> and no <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Faithful Shepherdeſs,</hi> and <hi>Philaſter,</hi> (notwithſtanding ſome faults found in them,) <hi>Philip Meſſenger</hi> had alſo the happineſs to be the Author of ſome good Plays, Sir <hi>John Suckling's Aglau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> Sir <hi>John Denham's Sophie,</hi> are very well Writ; Sir <hi>William Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant's,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Howard's</hi> Plays are generally good; but I am full of the great obligation we all owe (that love this innocent
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50736:36"/>diverſion) to my Lord <hi>Orrory,</hi> and to Mr. <hi>Dryden,</hi> for thoſe they have favour'd us, and adorn'd this Age with; for they have both equaled (in my opinion) the very beſt Authors in their's moſt excellent: And Mr. <hi>Dryden</hi> has much exceeded any of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, in the number of good Plays; And 'tis well for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that I have bid adeiu to the Muſes (and humor of Verſe) or elſe I ſhould have been troubleſome unto him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this occaſion, In telling him how very fond I am of his Plays, and how much they ought to be celebrated: And tho' Mr. <hi>Lee,</hi> (who I muſt name for <hi>Sophoniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi>'s ſake) and ſome other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, have Writ divers Good ones; Yet Mr. <hi>Dryden</hi> will be allowed to keep the Garland (without competitors, I think) both for the Excellency, and number of good Plays: And
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:50736:36"/>I foreſee, without the aſſiſtance of Aſtrology (or Spirit of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) that his <hi>Dramatick Poetry</hi> will be always the Sun in that Firmament; and himſelf the moſt illuſtrious Poet of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that kind.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:50736:37"/>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:50736:37"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Artemiſia</hi> to <hi>Iſocrates.</hi> THE FIRST HARANGUE OF Monſieur de <hi>Scuderie</hi>'s Firſt Volume of HEROICK HARANGUES.</head>
            <argument>
               <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
               <p>After <hi>Artemiſia</hi> had imployed the moſt expert Architects of her time, to Build that ſtately Tombe, which was ſince one of the ſeven wonders of the World; the love that ſhe had for her dear <hi>Mauſolus,</hi> being not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied: She then made to come from <hi>Greece, Iſocrates</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pompus,</hi> the moſt celebrated Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Antiquity; and by a Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:50736:38"/>truly Royal, ſhe obliged theſe great men, to make uſe of all their Eloquence, in favour of the King her Husband, to externize his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory. It was then to demand this kindneſs, that this Fair diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Lady, ſpake to 'em in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, when the exceſs of her love, had made her forget, that ſhe ſpake to the Famous <hi>Iſocrates.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <head>Artemiſia <hi>to</hi> Iſocrates.</head>
            <p>IT is from you, O Illuſtrious Orator, that I expect the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of <hi>Mauſolus;</hi> it is in you to give life to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue that I have erected to him; it is in you to make him a monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which the Revolution of time, can never deſtroy, and which will eternize it for ever: think not that I believe that either time or fortune, reſpect Gold, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Jaſper, Porphyry, or Oriental
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:50736:38"/>Alablaſter, which I have imployed to build this ſuperb ſtructure: No, I know that theſe three hundred Columns, of whom all the Orders are obſerved with care, and the Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es are ſo well fixt, and the Chapiters are ſo magnificent, and whereof the workmanſhip exceeds the materials, ſhall be one day but pitiful ruins, and at laſt reduced to little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and all the imboſſed Images which make and adorne the four fronts of this Sepulchre, ſhall be ſucceſſively defaced, by the very injury of the ſeaſon and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difficulty hereafter, ſhall there be ſome imperfect Figures perceived of all that which we do admire at this day. Theſe obelisks, who ſeem to defie the Tempeſts, ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſtruck with Lightning, and by it reduced to Aſhes; theſe Vaſes ſmoaking with incenſe, theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſht Flamboes, theſe Trophies of Armes, and all the ornaments whereof Architecture is capable,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:50736:39"/>cannot hinder the diſtruction of this Work. In fine <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> when I have employed all my Treaſures, on't, when by the skilful hands of <hi>Scopus,</hi> of <hi>Brixis,</hi> of <hi>Timothus,</hi> and of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chares,</hi> I have put it into an Eſtate, to paſs for one of the marvails of the World, if, after all that, ſome one do not take care to conſerve it in memory, by his writings, the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of Gold that I have erected, the Marble, Jaſper, Porphyry, Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſter, the Columns, the Images, the Obelisks, the Vaſes, the Flamboes and all the ornaments of Archite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, which appear in this work, hinder not, I ſay, that <hi>Mauſolus</hi> his Tombe, his Architects, his Sculp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and <hi>Artemiſia</hi> her ſelf be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in oblivion, and be as unknown to the ages afar off, as if they had never been: It is then in you <hi>Iſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates;</hi> it is then in you O <hi>Theopom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> to give this edifice its moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid foundation: It is in you, to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate theſe Marbles, by magnificent
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:50736:39"/>inſcriptions; it is in you, to reſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate <hi>Mauſolus;</hi> It is in you to make me live eternally, altho I feel that I ſhall dye very ſoon; I demand not of you <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> that you give me the praiſes of <hi>Helen,</hi> or the Eulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of <hi>Buſires,</hi> (tho' perhaps they have ſomtimes had their Penegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks.) I ſhall give you a more eaſie and a more illuſtrious Theam; the vertues of <hi>Mauſolus</hi> and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal affection of <hi>Artemiſia;</hi> this is a more noble ſubject, than the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity of <hi>Buſires,</hi> and the Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Helen;</hi> your Eloquence ſhall have no crimes to diſguiſe: All the Artifices that Rhetorick teaches, to impoſe deceits, and render 'em like truth, ſhall not ſerve you, but to perſuade verity, and without bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing any thing of the Sophiſts, it ſhall ſuffice that you write as an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, as a Philoſopher, and as an Hiſtorian altogether. Eloquence, that Gift that the Gods have grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to men, as a Ray of their own
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:50736:40"/>divinity, ought never to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, but to protect the innocent, or to eternize vertue; thoſe who made a Godeſs of <hi>Perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> never deſigned to render her a ſlave to the capricio's of men; and they knew without doubt (bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than I) that Eloquence is a gift of Heaven, that they ought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to profane the power that ſhe hath either of exciting, or appeaſing the moſt violent paſſions, to move the hearts of the moſt perverſe, to perſuade the moſt incredulous, to force the moſt obſtinate, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain 'em to their wills; and to make us oppoſe our ſelves, and quit our own opinions to follow thoſe of another: All theſe advantages I ſay, have not been given to men, to ſerve themſelves of 'em to unjuſt purpoſes; on the contrary it is ſhe whom the Gods have choſen to make vertue appear to the World, as Fair as ſhe is, and to make new conqueſts daily for her: It is by her that thoſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:50736:40"/>that poſſeſs her, acquire immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and immortalize others; it is ſhe who maugre the times, and the viciſſitute of things, conſerves the memory of fair actions; it is ſhe who maugre the devaſtation of Kingdoms, and Empires, continues the remembrance of Kings, and Emperors; and when that their Aſhes themſelves are no more in their Tombs, when their Palaces, are deſtroyed; when their moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Cities are deſerted, when their Statues are reverſed, and when their Realms themſelves have chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Names, makes yet to be ſeen to all the Earth, an Image of their vertue; yes many ages af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have ceaſed to live, they live ſtill amongſt men; they have yet friends and ſubjects, they are conſulted for the good conduct of life, their good qualities are imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, they make 'em New Elogies; envy doth not Tarniſh their glory, they give 'em all the praiſes they
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:50736:41"/>merit, the veneration that they have for 'em is ſo much that it carries them with a great deal of reverence to the places where they have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited; and if there continues but ſome old ruins of their buildings, they reſpect that which time hath not reſpected; they look on 'em with pleaſure, and prefer 'em a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the magnificence of the modern and moſt famous Painters, adorn their Tables with theſe illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Ruins, and eternize their memory after
'em. <hi>Iſocrates</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not then if I deſire ſo paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately that your Eloquence, make a Panegyrick, for my dear Lord; I know in what eſteem it is in all <hi>Greece,</hi> and I foreſee with certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that it will do him juſtice: In future Ages, all the writings which carry the name of <hi>Iſocrates</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pompus</hi> ſhall be be revered of time, of fortune, and of all men; and that they ſhall paſs through all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and through all Ages, without
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:50736:41"/>doing 'em an injury (unleſs they be outraged) and they ſhall bring with 'em the reputation of thoſe of whom they have ſpoken; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps there will be found ſome illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious perſons, who, by the eſteem that they make of your works, ſhall make 'em ſpeak Tongues not yet invented, who by the light of your glory; will believe they encreaſe their own, by publiſhing yours. Speak then, <hi>Theopompus,</hi> Speak then <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> of the vertues of <hi>Mauſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> and of the love of <hi>Artemiſia,</hi> to the end that all men may ſpeak af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you: But imagine not that I mingle any ſentiment of vanity in the prayer that I make you: No <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> I will not that you ſeek, in my perſon, or in my life, wherewith to make me a magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Elogy; I will not that you ſpeak of my Illuſtrious Birth; I will not that you ſay, that I was Born to the Crown of <hi>Halycarnaſſus;</hi> I will not have you ſay that tho' a
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:50736:42"/>Woman, I have known the art to Reign, I will not that you tell poſterity, of the extraordinary eſteem that the Great <hi>Xerxes,</hi> had for me; I will not have you ſay that I made the Voyage into <hi>Greece</hi> with him; I will not that you make known, that I had the firſt place in his Council, and that my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was always followed; I will not have you ſpeak of the Exploits that I did in that War, no more than of the exceſſive price that the Athenians promiſed to thoſe that would put me into their hands. But I would only have you ſay that <hi>Artemiſia,</hi> was Queen of <hi>Caria,</hi> becauſe ſhe was eſpouſed to <hi>Mauſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> who was the King thereof. That <hi>Artemiſia</hi> above all other vertues, hath always loved that which is the moſt neceſſary to her Sex; that ſhe hath never had other paſſion, than that of perfectly loving her Huſband, and that after having loſt him, ſhe hath loſt the deſire of life,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:50736:42"/>and in fine that after this misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, <hi>Artemeſia</hi> hath had no other care, than to illuſtrate his memory, but after you have ſaid all theſe things, and have praiſed <hi>Mauſolus</hi> as much as he merited, and after you have depainted my dolour or (to ſay better) my deſpair, as great as it is, forget not to learn poſterity that having made to be built, the moſt ſuperb Monument, that hath ever been ſeen; I have not been able to find an Urn, that I thought worthy to conſerve his Aſhes in. Chryſtal, Alablaſter, and all the Precious Stones that nature hath ever produced, have not ſeemed ſufficient to witneſs my affection, although it be magnificent and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral, to give him an Urn of Gold cover'd with Diamonds, (but to give him a heart for an Urn) it muſt be only <hi>Artemeſia</hi> that would do it, it is there <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> that I ſhall incloſe the Aſhes, of my dear Lord; It is there <hi>Theopompus,</hi> that I ſhall
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:50736:43"/>put in <hi>depoſitum</hi> theſe dear reliques of my Lord; &amp; I expect with impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence till this Tombe be in an Eſtate to receive this living Urn, that I have given him. It is truly my heart which ought only to ſerve for an Urn to the Allies of my <hi>Mauſolus,</hi> and it ſeemeth to me that I ſhall give 'em a new life by putting 'em there: it ſeemeth to me alſo, that they communicate to me, the mortal coldneſs that I find therein; and, 'tis but juſt that <hi>Mauſolus,</hi> having been alway in my heart, as long as he liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he ſhould be there after his death. Perhaps if I had put his Aſhes in this Urn of Gold, covered with Precious Stones, perhaps I ſay, ſome unjuſt Conquerour, might come and open his Tombe, and with Profane and Sacrilegious hands carry away the Urn, and ſcatter his Aſhes in the Wind, and ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate mine from <hi>Mauſolus</hi>'s; but of the faſhion that I uſe 'em we ſhall be inſeperable: there is no Tyrant
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:50736:43"/>which can trouble my repoſe, ſince it is not he, who can divide me from my dear Lord: Behold <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> that which you ought to ſay, ſee <hi>Theopompus</hi> that which I would have you ſay of me; but for my dear Lord, forget nothing of all that which may be glorious to him, nor of all that which was effectually in him. Say that he was redoubted of his Enemies, loved of his Subjects, and in veneration with all his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Princes: Speak of all the great Qualities of his Soul, as well as of the graces that he had received from Nature: Praiſe his Valour in the War, his Sweetneſs in Peace, and his Juſtice, and Clemency, to all the World: In fine, form you the Idea of an accompliſht Prince, and you ſhall make the true Pourtrait of <hi>Mauſolus.</hi> But after all the things that you have ſaid of this Illuſtrious Huſband, ſpeak with fervour of the love that he had for me: decipher this paſſion, ſo ſtrong, ſo pure, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:50736:44"/>ſo faithful as it was, undeceive thoſe that believe that Crimes are the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nouriſhment of love, and who think a lawful paſſion, can either be long, ſtrong, or ſo agreeable; tell 'em that <hi>Mauſolus,</hi> and I, have given 'em an example which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys all their reaſonings and their experiences to the contrary, ſince that our love had ſo much of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, and no leſs fervour, and that it continued even unto death, to be infinitly agreeable. Speak then with Elogy, of this ſacred bond, which forced two vertuous perſons, to love one another eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally. But as much as is poſſible haſten to ſatisfie me, and imploy even all your Eloquence, to all thoſe who work on this Tombe, to uſe their utmoſt diligence to finiſh it, as ſoon as they can, for I find my work is almoſt conſummated, for the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Aſhes of my dear <hi>Mauſolus</hi> which remains, will be quickly conſumed, and then I have no more to do in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:50736:44"/>the world; all that which is on the earth beſides, cannot touch my ſpirit, I am inſenſible to every thing elſe, except dolour, and the only deſire that I have in my Soul, is to be rejoyned to my dear <hi>Mauſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> and to know certainly, that you take care of his glorie: and that of yours ought to oblige you thereunto, and alſo compaſſion ought to carry you to it; And if it were permitted, to propoſe other rewards, to Philoſophers, than the only pleaſure of well doing, I might deſire you to conſider what charge I have been at, in raiſing this magnificent Tombe; and pray you to judge from thence, that ſhe who diſpoſed of ſo much Treaſure on mute Marble, will not be ungrateful to you, when you ſpeak of the glory of her dear <hi>Mauſolus;</hi> but uſe what ſpeed you can to put an end to your works; for neither the Architects, nor you, can ſo ſoon end yours, as I
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:50736:45"/>ſhall mine: for if I am not much deceived, I ſhall dye ſoon enough, to permit you to illuſtrate the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyrick of <hi>Mauſolus,</hi> by the death of <hi>Artemeſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Effect of this Harangue.</head>
               <p>THIS Vertuous Queen ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained her deſire, <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> and <hi>Theopompus,</hi> ſpake ſo advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagiouſly of her Dear <hi>Mauſolus,</hi> that ſome have accuſed 'em as tho' they flattered for Silver. As to her it was not without reaſon that ſhee preſſed the Architects to haſten, for their Work was not ended on this Superb Tombe, when ſhe muſt have had a place in't. Thoſe which undertook this Miraculous Structure finiſht it, and it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a long time one of the
<pb facs="tcp:50736:45"/>marvels of the World: and the glory on't, had a more ſolid foundation than it, for it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues yet, in the memory of Men, with that of <hi>Mauſolus,</hi> and of the Illuſtrious <hi>Artemeſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:50736:46"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of Books, printed for <hi>Will. Cademan.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>Folio.</head>
               <item>AN Inſtitution of General Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, or the Hiſtory of the World, by <hi>William Howell.</hi> L. L. D. In two Vol.</item>
               <item>Hiſtorical Collections, or an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Account of the Proceedings of the four laſt Parliaments of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous Memory.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pharamond,</hi> a Romance, compleat, <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clelia,</hi> a Romance. <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Partheniſſa,</hi> compleat. <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Hiſtorical heroick Poem on the Life of the Right Honourable <hi>Thomas,</hi> Earl of <hi>Oſſory,</hi> (with his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture neatly engraven on a Copper Plate) Written by <hi>Elkanah Settle.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Quarto.</head>
               <item>An Hiſtorical Relation of the firſt Diſcovery of the Iſle of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:50736:46"/>
               <item>The Proteſtant Religion is a ſure Foundation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Charles,</hi> Earl of <hi>Derby.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Policy to ſuppreſs Monarchy. By a Perſon of Honour.</item>
               <item>A Warning-piece for the Unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: In two Viſitation Sermons. By <hi>Seth Buſhel.</hi> D. D.</item>
               <item>The great Efficacy and Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of good Example; eſpecially, in the Clergy. In a Viſitation Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, at <hi>Guilford.</hi> By <hi>Tho. Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb.</hi> D. D.</item>
               <item>A Sermon preached before the King. By <hi>Miles Barnes,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to his Majeſty.</item>
               <item>A Sermon preached at the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes at <hi>Lancaſter.</hi> By <hi>Hen. Pigot.</hi> B.D.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Plays.</head>
               <item>The Rivals, a Comedy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cataline</hi>'s Conſpiracy.</item>
               <item>Iſland Princeſs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Flora</hi>'s Vagaries.</item>
               <item>Town Shifts.</item>
               <item>Citizen turn'd Gentleman.</item>
               <item>Morning Ramble.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mackbeth.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:50736:47"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cambyſes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Empreſs of <hi>Morocco.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Herod</hi> nnd <hi>Mariamne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Notes on the Empreſs of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocco.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ibrahim.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paſtor fido.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Love and Revenge.</item>
               <item>Pope <hi>Joan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fatal Love.</item>
               <item>Careleſs Lovers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Engliſh</hi> Princeſs.</item>
               <item>Reformation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Rogue.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marcelia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Mall.</item>
               <item>Rehearſal.</item>
               <item>Mock Tempeſt.</item>
               <item>Dumb Lady.</item>
               <item>Gentleman Dancing-Maſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alcibiades.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dutch Lovers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Piſoe's</hi> Conſpiracy.</item>
               <item>Seige of <hi>Memphis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rival Kings.</item>
               <item>Conſtant Nymph.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:50736:47"/>
               <item>Wrangling Lovers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tom Eſſence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>French</hi> Conjurer.</item>
               <item>Wits led by the Noſe.</item>
               <item>Counterfeit Bridegroom.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Wells.</item>
               <item>Man of <hi>New-Market.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Conſpiracy.</item>
               <item>Match in <hi>Newgate.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Octavo <hi>and</hi> Twelves.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Hiſtory; or, the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences that hap'ned in the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> between <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Nitard:</hi> with all the Letters and Politick Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes relating to thoſe Affairs.</item>
               <item>Reflexions on Ancient and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Philoſophy.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Princeſs; or, the Dutcheſs Queen. A pleaſant No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</item>
               <item>Court Songs and Poems; being, an exact Collection.</item>
               <item>The Temple of Death; with other Poems. By a Perſon of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:50736:48"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hogan Moganides;</hi> or, the <hi>Dutch Hudibras.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Liquor <hi>Alchaheſt,</hi> or the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Diſſolvent or <hi>Paracelſus</hi> and <hi>Helmont,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>A Philoſophical Eſſay; or, the Hiſtory of Petrifaction. By Dr. <hi>Sherly.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gulielmi Ferarii de bello Batavico.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Quibbles. Very pleaſant.</item>
               <item>The Amours of <hi>Count Du Noys.</hi> A witty Novel.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Zaide,</hi> or the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Hiſtory. A Pleaſant Novel.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mazarine</hi>'s Memoirs. A Novel.</item>
               <item>Penitent <hi>Hermit.</hi> And <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monſieur. Two Witty Novels.</item>
               <item>Clark's Manual; a Book of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Saunders</hi> his Aſtrological Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anima Mundi,</hi> an Hiſtorical Narration of the Opinion of the Antients, concerning Man's Soul after this Life, according to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enlightened Nature.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:50736:48"/>
               <item>Hiſtory of the <hi>Pallas Royal;</hi> or, the Amours of <hi>Madamoiſelle de La Valiere.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Amours of <hi>Madame</hi> and Count <hi>de Guiche.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Copy of the two Journal Books of the Houſe of <hi>Commons;</hi> in which, is the whole Hiſtory of the late horrid Popiſh Plot.</item>
               <item>The Wits paraphras'd; or, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe upon Paraphraſe. In a Burleſque on the late ſeveral Tranſlations of <hi>Ovid</hi>'s Epiſtles.</item>
               <item>Two Diſcourſes. The firſt ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how the <hi>Chief Criterions</hi> of phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophical <hi>Truth,</hi> invented by <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative</hi> men, more eminently ſerve <hi>Divine</hi> Revelation, than either <hi>Philoſophy</hi> or <hi>Natural Religion.</hi> The <hi>ſecond,</hi> manifeſting how all the <hi>Foundations</hi> of the <hi>Intellectual World,</hi> viz. <hi>Reaſon, Morality, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> have been undermined by <hi>Popiſh</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Policies. By <hi>Tho. Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyngham,</hi> M. A. Fellow of <hi>New
<pb facs="tcp:50736:49"/>Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Rector of <hi>Eaſt Tyſted</hi> in <hi>Hantſhire.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Macchiavel Redivivus;</hi> being, an exact Diſcovery or Narrative of the Principles and Politicks of our be-jeſuited Modern Fanaticks.</item>
               <item>The preſent State of <hi>Geneva;</hi> with a brief Deſcription of that City, and the ſeveral Changes and Alterations it hath been ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to, from the firſt Foundation thereof.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
